Have you ever heard of the Moomin Valley?
During the winter it sleeps deep in the snowdrifts.
All the rational creatures hibernate when it is covered with snow.
This is the Moomin House.
Can you see? They are rational creatures.
This is MoominTroll. The hero of the story.
And this is MoominPappa.
And this is MoominMamma.
And this one is so little it has to be Little My.
You never know who you will find sleeping in the Moomin House.
But now it's time to start the story.
It might become boring if everyone is asleep.
So let's jump right to the spring time...
Spring! Spring has begun!
Ahoy everyone! It's spring!
MoominTroll!
Oh, are you awake too?
- Who can sleep while you're making noises?
I shouted because I was excited.
Tell me one thing...
- Yea, what?
Do you find it amusing to wake other people up?
Well of course!
- I just had a dream that I was living in a watermelon.
You have to get up. The sun is shining.
- Hmph! What's so special about it?
The winter is over. The spring is here. And life is wonderful!
Sleeping is wonderful too...
You told us to wake you up on the first day of spring.
- Did I?
Can't you remember?
- Not very well...
You can always go back to sleep if you want to.
No. I'm not tired at all anymore.
- There you go!
Mother!
- Happy spring time, MoominTroll.
MoominMamma! I'm hungry! Do you have watermelon?
No, but I have lots of other things. Let's prepare a big breakfast.
Snufkin is back!
If you used the stairs it would be faster!
It wouldn't be half as fun.
Are you going to your house?
- Yes. It was nice to spend the winter at your place.
Your sister isn't back yet.
- I will still go!
Snufkin!
- Hey MoominTroll.
This year you got back early.
- Could be.
Wasn't your trip fun?
- Yea. It was. But I sensed the spring had begun.
Tell me about your trip!
- Some other time, MoominTroll.
Let's go and wake up Sniff and do something special.
- Sniff doesn't like to be awoken.
I can hear snoring. I'm going to whistle one more time.
The snoring stopped...
Sniff come out! Snufkin is here!
- I want to sleep!
We are going to do something special.
- Oh, something special?
Maybe climbing on top of the hill is special.
- We could be the first ones to climb up.
On a day like this you should be able to see all of MoominValley from the top.
Good morning!
- Good morning! Are your parents up yet?
Mother is.
- A-hah! That weird habit of hibernating...
We enjoy it.
Why do we always have to do something special?
Beautiful!
- Isn't the view splendid?
Yea, there's smoke from the chimney of MoominHouse.
MoominMamma is making something good.
What?
- Someone has been here before us. Look!
Top hat...
Hmm, big and black. Who's is it?
MoominPappa could use it on Sundays.
Hmm. It's quite bigger than mine. Can you see?
It's difficult to see under this... It's deeper...
My old hat is better.
What's wrong?
The hat seems to have shrunk. I can't get it off!
- Let me help you.
My head has swollen!
What's wrong?
- The hat got stuck on father's head.
Your old hat is stylish enough.
- This isn't mine! The kids found it.
It sure is beautiful.
What are we going to do with it?
I don't like the hat at all.
Should we throw it out?
- That would be a pity!
Do you know someone big headed enough?
- I don't. It's good here.
Oh, a trash bin.
- Good guess, Snufkin.
Now let's eat breakfast. Come along, Snufkin.
Lovely smell...
I'm going out with MoominTroll.
Do you want to come along?
Or would you rather stay here?
What? Are you coming or not?...
So you're not coming?
Nisku...
- It's almost ready now!
This year my flying machine is going to be ready!
It still needs a final touch.
I wonder if it's even possible to build the flying machine?
- Of course not.
Nisku has dreamed about building it.
- You can always dream.
I'm content with smaller dreams.
- So am I.
Don't you ever stop eating? You probably don't dream about anything.
I dream about an empty cupboard.
Hmm, I wonder who has been eating eggs in here...
It's good that we finally have the trash bin.
What are these?
- They look like clouds.
Don't touch! They might be poisonous!
I'm floating!
- Lovely!
I want to try too.
- Are you comfortable?
Let's go!
What if you fall down? What if the clouds go high and someone falls down?
Hey, small cloud, wait for me... I'm falling down.
MoominPappa is writing his memoirs.
Lots of things have happened to him.
The memoirs will be vast.
Heavens! MoominTroll!
What on earth are you doing?
- Father, I'm flying! These clouds came from the house.
Come closer. I'll save you.
- No need.
Wait! Stop!
- Father, jump on board!
I'm afraid.
- Jump or you will fall!
Too late!
Mother, emergency!
- What is it?
Do you know what the kids are doing?
- Yes I know.
They are sailing on top of clouds!
- I told them to be careful so they won't fall.
Sniff, are you ready?
I won!
Wait cloud, come back!
Be kind and do not move... Just like that...
Stay still, cloud...
We will play together again, cloud.
Come! Come here, cloud!
My cloud is vanishing.
That was fun.
- But I haven't had enough yet!
Are MoominTroll and Snork Maiden up there?
Their clouds last longer!
- But they are vanishing too. They should come down.
I'll start to count. One...
Little My. Do you want something?
- A good place to hide!
Are there good hiding places in here?
No. He will find me in here...
MoominTroll has to be in the house.
- I saw him going into the fireplace.
Did you find him already?
- I didn't.
Did you check from the basement?
- Of course.
Did someone just laugh?
- Who?
I have to go home now.
Is there something wrong?
- Yes. We haven't found MoominTroll yet.
He's so fat he couldn't fit in a good hiding place.
The laughing comes from there!
Here I am!
I think I'm the only one who wasn't found.
Who are you?
- You don't recognize me?
You were looking for me so hard... And couldn't find...
Be kind and introduce yourself.
I see. Is this a new game?
I am Snork Maiden. Who are you?
- I am the King of MoominValley!
You are so ugly you can't be a king.
- That was unfriendly. Wasn't it, father?
Do you know where MoominTroll is?
- I'm here.
Where?
- Here.
Now you really have to say who you are!
Father...
- I am not your father.
Yes you are. I am MoominTroll.
- MoominTroll is kind and handsome. Unlike you.
Have you seen yourself in the mirror?
What does this mean? My snout is gone!
I'm all furry and my tail thick and furry!
I'm dreaming! This can't be true!
This is too much!
What are you screaming about? What has happened?
Mother!
- What on earth...
He claims to be MoominTroll.
Is this really my Moomin child?
- I am! I really am! Don't you believe?
Are you?
- I might have changed somehow!
Calm down. There's nothing to worry about if you really are MoominTroll.
Say it if you really think I am MoominTroll. I don't know what to think about this but I really am MoominTroll!
Mother, say it, I'm your own MoominTroll. Say it!
Don't I recognize my own child?
You really are my own Moomin child.
- Oh mother!
Oh MoominTroll...
Father...
Poor MoominTroll. Where did you go to hide?
- The hat...
Better get rid of the hat.
Because everyone wanted to keep their present form of existence they decided to get rid of the hat.
MoominTroll was not fully content with the decision. You don't find a hat like that every day.