Snufkin prefers to live on his own.
This year he has set up his tent next to the creek.
He will stay there at peace with the world until winter.
MoominTroll sometimes feels lonely and enjoys the company of Snufkin.
Snufkin?
- Snufkin!
He's not here.
- He has forgotten and left to wander.
Why does he like to be alone?
- I also like to be alone sometimes.
Should we go our separate ways?
- Rather tomorrow.
We decided to go today.
- Yes we did. You can't sneak out from a mutual decision.
You decided, not me.
- You were there also. You have to come and look for the seashells too.
I'm already going!
It's Sniff!
Where are you going?
- I envy Snufkin.
Why?
- Just because.
I wonder where he is...
Maybe we will find something as interesting as the hat.
- Yea it was something...
Did you really throw it in the river? You shouldn't...
- It seemed to be dangerous.
The hat transformed me into a tarsier.
- And the eggshells into clouds.
Yea that was fun.
I'm going to see if I can find a shell with a pearl!
MoominTroll! Wake up. Snork Maiden is in trouble!
What? What's wrong?
- Snork Maiden fell into Antlion's hole when we were playing tag. Come!
Push a little more!
- Give me your hand! Give me your hand!
Antlion!
Are you trying to mess up my hole?
- No, I'm just leaving...
Stop immediately! You will scare my prey.
Snork Maiden, is everything okay?
- I just can't reach her.
I might not be eating ants today.
- MoominTroll help!
Sniff, drop into the hole.
- What? Me?
Don't be afraid. I'm here.
- You're tall enough to do this. Go!
I'm going to eat you all!
Sniff, quick!
- But I...
-- Go now you fool!
Go yourself, fool.
Snork Maiden, grab his foot!
Help, it's my tail!
Grab onto me.
- Thank you!
Are you ready?
My tail hurts!
I know a secret.
- Tell me.
The Magician's hat has floated to a sandbank.
- Really?!
There's weird things happening.
- Oh no.
You should have thrown it elsewhere.
- Yes. The creek was not a good place.
It's stuck there in the tree.
I don't quite see but the water has turned red.
I think the water has changed into something else.
Let's go get the hat.
- Hopefully the red colour goes away.
Are you going to be okay?
Did you find the hat?
- Yes I did.
Raspberry juice!
What are we going to do with the hat?
We cannot just leave it. You don't know who will crawl into it.
But we can drink raspberry juice whenever we pour water into the hat.
Maybe the water turned into raspberry juice because it was from this river.
We should test it.
MoominTroll, you look tired.
- I woke up and couldn't get back to sleep.
Nonsense!
- What do you mean?
I know what you were doing. I was up too. You were with Snufkin.
You have been dreaming. I'm busy. Thanks for breakfast.
I know what you did. I know!
- It's boring listening to someone explain their dreams.
What's going on?
- It's nothing, MoominPappa.
Oh he left again...
You don't keep a secret from Little My!
Snufkin!
I know who the hat belongs to.
Who?
- The Magician.
The Magician?!
- I just saw Hemulen and he told me he saw The Magician.
I had a dream about a flying witch...
- On the back of a black panther?
The only thing he cares about are rubies. He searches the world for them atop his black panther.
And when he lost his hat...
- He must have been in Moomin Valley searching for rubies.
I wonder if The Magician has more hats.
- I don't know.
He might not know where he has lost his hat.
- It must be so.
I want to try one thing with the hat.
- What thing? Tell me.
Antlion's aren't worth their reputation.
- It takes hours before they bury themselves into the sand.
It takes only an hour.
- You're lying now...
One hour is a long time to bury yourself in the sand.
Are you talking about me?
We are talking about how fast you can bury yourself into the sand.
Faster than you can imagine.
MoominTroll said you can do it in an hour but I don't believe it.
Snufkin says that you need hours to bury yourself.
I can show you!
Quite fast. Can't say otherwise.
- Yea that was quick, but she already has a hole dug in the sand.
No there's not!
- Oh yea?
I can dig myself anywhere. Anywhere!
I think this is a good place.
- I think so too. Here, under this rock...
Hah! Show me the place!
- Dig here.
Exactly here...
- Time me.
Ahoy! A second and a half!
That's something!
- Yes it is.
I'll sit on top just in case.
- Good. Try now to escape...
So you caught the Antlion?
- Little My!
I know what you're doing...
- Did you follow us last night?
Of course.
- Have you told the others?
Fool! But wake me up next time.
Or otherwise you will tattle? Is that what you mean?
You'll wake me up because I'm nice.
- Ah, that's another thing...
Look! Water!
I can't see the hat.
- Well, no indeed. Where did you last use it?
What a lot of water...
- I think the sand has turned into water.
I think the Antlion has turned into something.
- I think so too.
I've sat here long enough. I'll jump off!
I think I can remove the rock myself.
Do we have to help him to get out?
- This is horrifying!
Well, let's get it done.
What has happened to her?
- Let's turn the hat over.
The spring of life!
Mother!
Hedgehog.
MoominTroll.
Don't push me.
- Be quiet!
I just saw a magician.
- It must have been him.
Was he looking for his hat?
- I'm afraid so. Did you hide it well?
In the basement.
- Is it a safe hiding place?
Only Little My and I know where the hat is.
A piece of string.
That could turn into spaghetti.
It didn't turn into spaghetti.
MoominMamma! MoominMamma! You should know one thing.
What thing?
- There's something going on in the house.
In our house?
- There's a tree growing in the basement!
Well that's lovely.
What on earth have you done?
- I just put a piece of string into The Magician's hat...
But we threw the hat away.
- We took it back and put it in the basement.
Who is "us"?
- Me and MoominTroll... It sure is growing beautifully.
We have to tell MoominPappa before it's too late.
Come in. The door isn't locked.
Don't worry, just keep on growing. Who would have imagined I was such a green thumb.
Tell me when you need water. And grow fruit soon!
Come in.
- Sorry to disturb you.
What's wrong?
- Bad news.
Oh, bad news?
- You should come downstairs to see it for yourself before it's too late.
Too late? Sounds threatening, but don't worry I'll take care of you.
Come MoominMamma.
Leave my husband's writing desk alone!
I'm coming, my dear!
Could you bring me the saw? This is a catastrophe!
Unfortunately the saw is in the basement and it is not possible to go there.
Back to the nature then. I'll break the vines with my hands!
Oh, Moomin House!
- Come Snork Maiden, this is fun!
But what has happened?
- I have been gardening.
Catastrophe's shouldn't last this long. I want to have breakfast!
There's a bright side: We don't need any more firewood.
You will learn not to take over the Moomin House just like this...
MoominPappa! MoominPappa! Look! Flowers! And fruits!
MoominPappa, try these...
Horrible!
- Little My has definitely put something into the hat.
MoominTroll, where are you?
Snork Maiden.
- Oh, MoominTroll, I was afraid you were inside.
Father! Mother! Little My!
- We have to get saws and axes.
Saws and axes are in the basement and we cannot go there.
- I will run for help.
There's no need.
Are you The Magician?
- Yes. I notice that you have found my hat.
It was on the top of a mountain.
- That's weird. I thank that the tree is growing well.
You shall fade away now!
You have quite a hat.
- Yes, it is. I apologise.
We are thankful that you saved us.
That's nice of you to say.
Have you happened to see any unusually large rubies here?
The hat being here seems to be an omen.
Here you go. It was a present from my husband.
It's very pretty, but it's not the king ruby I am looking for.
King ruby?
- I've been looking for it for hundreds of years but I cannot find it. I am obsessed with it.
We will light a signal fire if we find it.
- That is very nice of you. I think we will see each other again.
He wasn't that bad.
Let's start to pile the firewood.
- Understood!
And so The Magician's hat disappeared from Moomin Valley.
MoominTroll's parents were happy about it, but MoominTroll missed the unlimited raspberry juice.