Peace has come back to Moomin Valley again. No worries are to be seen.
Or, just wait a moment...
MoominTroll! MoominTroll wait!
Mother! Mother, are they ready?
- Is what ready?
The pancakes!
- Not ready yet. The Magician's wood doesn't burn well.
You're only making the dough now...
Pancakes don't take long.
- Are the pancakes ready?!
There's not much to worry about...
I am a fool! Stupid!
- No you're not. You are wise.
I'm a rotten egg! Dumb!
- Your machine goes well on the land, right?
If you can design a machine that moves on land you can surely make one that flies. I believe in you.
I'm not much good for anything...
Last night I thought I finally succeeded with the flying machine.
But then I looked at my papers and I thought how can I be so simple minded when I'm so intelligent!
I'm a complete fool...
The pancakes are ready. Go and tell everyone.
- I can go.
Where are MoominTroll and Snork Maiden?
- Snork Maiden is crying again.
Don't take it so seriously. Inventors get depressed when their inventions don't work.
MoominPappa also invents stories, right?
- Yes, or memorials.
Snork Maiden, would you like a pancake?
- Yes please!
MoominTroll, go and get your Father. He is stuck again with his writing.
Snork Maiden, what's wrong?
When the morning came the sun rolled on the eastern side of the sky and slowly everything got brighter...
Even the stupidest reader knows that... Oh I don't have any writing skills...
I'm not a professional... I better quit...
Come in!
Father?
- What is it?
Mother says the pancakes are ready.
- I'm fighting with creativity. I'll come later.
Did you have anything else?
- No. Yes... Maybe I misheard...
MoominTroll! Wait, I will come!
That tasted good. I will go out!
I will come too.
- No, Snufkin and I are going on a dangerous adventure.
Hey, Snufkin!
- Hey you, I thought you were never coming.
What's that?
- A leaf boat. It sails down the river.
It goes all the way to the ocean and washes on the shore of unknown lands.
- One day I will make a boat trip too.
Are we ready to go?
- Little My wants to come too but I said it's too dangerous.
You should have chosen your words more carefully. Look!
Hey, wait! These ones also need excitement in their lives!
- Wait!
Are we really going to climb on top of that mountain?
- I don't think we can manage it?
I'm not going up...
- But I am!
Wouldn't you rather keep me company?
- Couldn't you girls just wait for us in the cave next to the path?
Couldn't you just walk along the path?
- Girls have difficulty understanding these things.
Boys are difficult to understand.
We want to climb.
- Let's go already.
Are you coming with us, Sniff?
- I'll protect the cave from below.
Coward...
- Don't underestimate me. Someone has to stay with the girls.
Should we go into the cave?
- I don't feel like going in...
It's better to stay here. You never know who lives in a cave.
- You fools, there's no one living in there!
Exactly. That's why I don't feel like going in.
- Uninhabited places are horrifying...
I think we should be right above the cave but I don't see the hole.
- Maybe it's a bit further.
Wow! I've never seen seashells like these before! This has to be valuable! Little My, come here!
Where is Little My?
- She went into the cave.
Horrible... She should come and pick the seashells.
Little My! Come out!
- Come on you coward!
It's dangerous to just go in like that.
Then how on earth would you get in?
- Wait there. We will come and save you.
Aren't you coming with me, Snork Maiden?
Yea... I think so...
- Well let's go then.
I'll take your hand in case you start to be afraid.
Where are you, Little My? Answer!
You'll make Snork Maiden afraid!
Oh, I thought I'll make you scared. Your voice is shaking.
- My voice sounds like this all the time!
Shh, I hear something...
I hear something too. Maybe the wind?
- It sounds like someone is sobbing.
Don't scare me! No one is living here!
It's just Snufkin and MoominTroll. They have come down into the cave.
- Why would they sob? It has to be someone else.
Oh, stop Little My!
Pull now, MoominTroll.
- Is it okay now?
Which one of us goes first?
- Me.
Be careful.
- Understood.
Take it easy. There's no hurry.
Hey, are you okay?
- Of course!
MoominTroll! Are you okay?
- I think so. But, my bottom hurts...
Who screamed?
- Our friend Hemulin was here taking a nap.
Oh, heavens...
Are you playing games again?!
- We didn't know you were here taking a nap.
I didn't lay down for a nap.
- Then what were you doing here?
To be honest, I haven't been myself lately.
- Have you lost a rare stamp again?
On the contrary, I have them all. Every single stamp that a collector can have.
Then what's wrong?
- My stamp collection is perfect.
No one has a better collection than you.
Of course not, mine is the best. There are no rarities that I don't own.
Then I don't understand.
- You are too young to understand. And besides, you are not collectors.
I'm starting to get it...
- What?
Hemulin is no longer a collector, just an owner, and it's not nearly as fun.
- The fun is gone...
Ah, you have tense nerves and me falling on your neck didn't make you feel better.
- Honestly speaking, no.
Hemulin was taking a nap in the cave.
- Poor Hemulin.
Hah! The ghost sobbing was Hemulin snoring.
I never snore!
- Yes you do!
If you don't tell anyone I will show you an extraordinary thing...
- What is it?
Oh boy!
- Is that it?
Isn't it gorgeous?
- It's beautiful!
I wonder if someone owns it.
Maybe it could be fixed.
- Of course, and it's not even difficult.
You never know... The bottom seems rotten.
- I'm sure it's sailable.
The sail has holes in it.
- The oars are missing.
We don't need them, we will row with our hands.
- You will!
Look out! The boat is tipping!
I have lost my self confidence and it feels so bad...
- That could happen to anyone.
To you too?
- Yes, but not very often.
How can I get my self confidence back?
- I don't know, mine usually comes with time.
I doubt I will ever make another contraption...
- I think I will leave the memoirs for a while.
What's wrong with both of you? You look so gloomy.
I was too confident.
- Me too.
Hey! Moominpappa! Moominpappa!
- What's wrong, Nipsu? We can hear you without howling...
Come quickly! We have found a boat at the shore!
Oh, did you find a shipwreck on the shore?
- No. it's a real boat. It has a sail!
We will fix the boat and then it will be ours.
I'm coming. Come Snork, an adventure is what you need now.
- Yea, maybe. I could be interested in a boat if it has a sail.
Hmm, yes, a brisk little boat...
- It has a good shape.
Dad, isn't it ours because it is abandoned?
Hmm, maybe it has been left here because it leaks.
That would be understandable.
- Yes, but finders always become owners!
Well it's not always like that. First we have to wait a little.
- Then what we will we do, father?
Well we have to fix the boat so we can anchor it if a storm surprises us.
Of course!
- But if the owner shows up I don't think we will give up on the boat... It might be that no one actually knows where the boat is.
What will we do after we fix it?
- Pity those boats that are left on the shore. What about sailing the seven seas?
I want to see the rest of the world.
- I also want to look around.
And you don't have to be afraid. If we encounter big waves we just sail between them, right Moominpappa?
Just like that. Okay, my friends, let's begin. Will you help with the planning, Snork?
- Yes of course.
Moominpappa, can I do something?
- Would you really like to?
Well if you don't mind, but I'm not that handy...
But first we have to draw it in the sand.
- Yea! Let's do it!
We need at least 10 logs under the boat.
- Yea we're going!
Then we need a few bigger logs for support.
We also need lots of nails.
- That's true, and also a bucket and hand bailer.
I'll help to pick up the nails because it's a difficult thing.
- And I will look after the boat in case the owner shows up.
The sails...
- What?
Are the kids asleep already?
- They sleep like logs.
No wonder, they worked so hard.
I can't wait until we sail somewhere.
- Oh, I'll take you anywhere in the world! Anywhere!
I don't fancy going far.
- Should we go to sleep? It's an early morning tomorrow... Oh working outside is hard.
It's going to be okay.
- Poor thing, sailing will do good for you...
Good job, If I say so myself.
- And now the rest...
Listen, Moomintroll, I will tar the boat.
- Yea yea, I will just tar where you can't reach.
Sniff, go and get some more tar for us.
- Huh, go and get it yourself! I let you tar the boat only because you wanted to.
Getting the tar is not my job! Go on and stop whining!
Should I cut it from here, Moominmamma?
- Yes, right there.
What's wrong, Hemmulin?
- The boat things seem be progressing quickly.
Yes it's going to be ready soon.
- That's what I was afraid of...
What am I supposed to do then?
- Can't you find another thing to collect?
Like what?
- Anything. Collect butterflies...
No way. My cousin collects them and he's a total fool.
Decorations?
- Decorations!
You could collect them forever.
- Unscientific!
I really think you should start collecting something.
Hurry up! We are going to christen the boat!
- I'm coming! I'm coming!
You fixed the sail really well. Come!
Are you ready? Push! One, two, three!
When the boat was fixed and the previous owner had not shown up Moomintroll started to get excited about the upcoming trip. Even Sniff and Hemulin were in good spirits.
And now for a test sailing...
I have decided what I will collect next. Flowers. This beautiful flower is my first collectors item.
- Great, Hemulin!
Snorkmaiden, I think I will go home. I just got an idea for my flying machine! I think I can make it work now.
That's for sure.
- See you later!
Take the ropes off and start rowing.
Mamma, we will come back for supper.
- You don't need to. I'll prepare cold snacks.