Moomintroll and his friends were about to have a trip with the boat that they had found from the shore.
They had not decided the destination yet as it was more fun to travel that way.
My darling, we will be coming back...
- Let's hope so.
You never know about the sea...
- Well no, but...
We have to build a fire when we get there.
- We can collect wood from the island.
Yes, but it's annoying if it's raining or the island is barren.
It's not an adventure then.
- Camping life could be nice too.
Hey! Hurry up!
Moomintroll!
- Hey Snork Maiden!
You could have fallen!
- Nonsense!
You should be more careful or you will hurt yourself.
That was good practice. Is your brother coming?
- No, he's too focused on his blueprints.
Oh boy! We will get to sail with a real sailing boat!
Is it ready yet?
- It doesn't look like it.
Are we taking all of this with us?
- Unfortunately yes. It's your mother's idea.
Moomintroll where are we going?
- That's what we don't know.
Hemulin! Did you find some rarity?
No, I'm afraid I already have this one in my collection... Jeez, are you moving somewhere?
- We're going on a boat trip.
Oh yea? And no one is against it?
- No.
But then why do you need so much stuff?
To the sails! Anchor up! To the sails!
Aren't the Moomins here yet?
- No.
Isn't it a lovely day?
- Where are we going?
It's not decided yet.
- I don't want to go anywhere far.
Why?
- I'm not a good swimmer and if the boat capsizes I would be a burden...
Look at the weather. There's no chance of a storm.
Thanks. Everybody on the boat! Moominmamma, My, Snufkin, Snork Maiden, Hemulin. Let's go.
Are you going too?
- Moominpappa said we could stop on an island and I could collect rare plants.
Hurry up, Sniff.
The boat is full.
- You will also fit.
This will take the whole day.
- I might be the drop that breaks the camels back.
You fool, the boat would carry much more.
Do you see?
- One more can fit. Can't it, Father?
Of course. The sea is almost calm.
- Let's leave it for the next time...
Let him whine on the shore. Let's go!
Sniff will you be okay?
- Why wouldn't I? I think someone has to stay and take care of the Moomin House.
Aren't you so thoughtful. There's cake on the kitchen table.
- Don't worry about me!
Sniff should have come too.
- Sniff is a coward.
He's not a very good swimmer. And he also eats too much.
This is life!
- Yes it is.
Oh, we lost the wind.
We have to start rowing.
- Yes. Snufkin, take the oar.
Row faster!
- I am rowing fast.
We aren't moving.
- Yes we are, but slowly.
I wish you were rowing slaves.
- The current must be against us.
If this goes on I won't find any new plants.
- Throw a hook in the water and collect some seaweed.
Wish for the wind. Many seamen have drowned when the sea is serene.
- Look, there is an island!
It's too small to do anything there.
- Not for me!
We are moving even if I don't row.
- The wind has picked up.
Look, a beautiful island!
- And a good looking place to harbour.
I bet there are plenty of unknown plants.
- And beasts and cannibals.
I'll build an stove so I can start preparing coffee. Someone can go to the shore and look for driftwood.
Father, I will jump to shore with the rope.
These things came in handy.
- We live a comfortable camping life.
Perhaps we are the first ones to visit this island.
Oh thank you!
What else?
- The island should be investigated.
I'll go explore.
- Explore everything.
Are you coming with me?
- I'll stay with Moominmamma.
Here comes wood for the sailors.
- That is a lot of wood.
I think the island is uninhabited.
- I wouldn't be surprised. I haven't seen anyone.
But I have.
- Who?
-- Middle sized. White.
What do you mean by "middle sized"?
- Like me.
What did it look like?
- White, as I already said. Like a ghost.
I bet it's just your imagination.
- Don't you believe me?!
I do. I do believe you think you saw something.
3 stems and 7 pistils. Interesting foundation...
And that has to be...
Oh, what a foundation. This island boasts rarities.
Well, I wonder what that is...
My dear lord... A barometer. It shows rain and storms. It must be broken.
Hey, what creatures are you then? Oh, it's your barometer.
Go away! Do not stomp on the plants!
I think My has seen a Hattifattener.
Do Hattifatteners look like ghosts?
- Yes they do a bit, but they are harmless.
Someone clearly called for help.
- I bet it was Hemulin.
Ah, go away! Help! Help!
What a lot of Hattifatteners.
- Poor Hemulin.
Help me get down!
What have you done? The Hattifatteners are angry.
Nothing else but knocked on this pole.
I don't think that is what made them angry.
- I also knocked the barometer to see what the weather is.
Maybe the Hattifatteners thought you were going to steal the barometer.
Snufkin, tell them I don't want the barometer!
- How are we going to drive them away?
Hurry up, I'm falling!
- We have to do something.
I'm thinking...
- Hurry up!
Now I know! Hattifatteners cannot hear or see well, but their sense of touch is very good. Rock the pole!
Like this?
- Harder!
Do you see? They feel the vibration. Keep on rocking the pole.
My hands are heavy as lead. I'm falling!
The rocking seems to be effective.
Are you okay?
- Nasty creatures.
I'll take their lowsy barometer.
- I don't think that is wise.
This isn't even working.
- How do you know?
It's terrific weather but this forecasts a storm.
Real pancakes instead of canned food.
- I know what's needed for the trip.
Moominpappa knows how to plan everything.
The barometer shows low pressure.
- It will be a storm.
A horrible storm... What if the barometer isn't functioning properly?
- Hmm, Hemulin, it might be functioning.
Look at the horizon.
A storm is arriving.
- Better leave before it hits us.
There's no time. We will be in distress.
We will have time.
- It would be a waste to leave so soon. We have not even explored the other side of the island.
I want to explore the Hattifatteners.
- I don't. I definitely don't.
I think we should leave.
- What do you think Mamma?
My dear, you are the captain.
- Good. Let me think.
We stay.
- Really?
Hurry up. We need to put up the tent.
A tent?
- Of course. Moominmamma has packed a tent.
Has she? Mother, you're the best!
First we fold the sail and bring the boat onto the beach.
Ready.
I don't think the waves will come this far. Next, the tent. Do not loiter.
Poor Hemulin. Maybe this task is too hard for you. Sit there and rest.
I'm exhausted.
- I'll go to put up the tent. Stay here and rest but when you get up remember to tie the boat to the tree.
You can count on me.
Well let's get to work.
Poor Hemulin...
Oh, I haven't seen this one before...
This one must be rare.
Snufkin! How does it look like?
- Above the sea there is a grey curtain. It will rain soon.
Let's go before we get wet.
No, not yet.
Now what?
- It's so exciting!
It's great to stand here with the sea swirling and watch the approaching storm.
Yea?
- Yea. And at the right time.
So at the right time not to get wet?
- Exactly.
I wonder what the Hattifatteners will do.
- They will wait for the storm.
What for?
- They will become electrified during the storm.
Really? Oh, it's raining.
The hardest rain of my life.
- It won't last long.
Moomintroll, you're dripping wet.
- Thank you.
Don't be afraid. You'll be safe with me.
The lightning hit close...
- Sure.
The storm is over, Snork Maiden.
An excellent catch of the day.
If you are stuck on an uninhabited island you can do nothing else besides wait for the storm to pass.
But if the waves and rising water take the boat to the open sea it won't be good.