Letters are nice to receive. At least every now and then.
Letters are rare in Moomin Valley, but they have post boxes and even a postman.
Did you call for me?
There's a letter for you.
- Fall in! Fall in!
Now he's coming. Fall in! Fall in!... It worked!
Did you dig that hole?
- Yes! And it worked!
Who did this trick?!
Are you hurt?
- Did you dig this hole?!
Of course not.
- Then who?
You little!...
- Mr. Postman, can I get the letter please?
Stop! You annoying bully!
Mother! A letter came.
- My dear! A letter?
From Mymble.
Where's My?
- She is running around somewhere.
Tell me about the letter. It's from my sister Mymble, right?
- I don't know.
She went to have a vacation from me, but I guess now she is coming back.
- No she's not if she has any sense. I fell into the hole for the third time.
I know. But the first two times I didn't see.
- You are an annoying bully!
I almost fell!
- Good.
You awful child! Nothing good will happen to you!
Mymble is coming back. She feels better now.
- Terrific.
We should go to clean Mymble's house.
- Does Little My know that her sister is coming back?
No. I think the postman is still chasing her.
- Nevermind telling me why.
MoominMamma, is the letter from Mymble? What is she writing?
After a few days Mymble got back to Moomin Valley.
Mymble is much bigger and calmer than My.
There is Moomin Valley.
Is it full of evil creatures?
- Not that I know of.
Look there is smoke. Smoke means food.
- That is Moomin House.
Are you on your way to Moomin House too?
- Yes, that's what we thought.
Well that's a coincidence. I'm going there too.
Your suitcase looks heavy. Do you want me to help carry it?
- No! Never!
Well, okay then.
- What kind of people live in Moomin House?
Do you plan to stay overnight?
- If they are nice.
They are very nice. My little sister lives with them.
What's wrong?
- You go ahead.
Fine.
How are you?
- I'm fine. Have you rested up? Come! Everybody is waiting for you!
By the way, there are two little strangers coming here.
- Here?
Yes. They are about My's size and carrying a large suitcase.
- I'll make really small beds for them.
Well thanks for the coffee. Come, My, let's go home.
- Not yet...
We have to go and clean the house. The rooms have to be aired out.
- I wiped the floors yesterday and left the windows open.
It must have been easy when you have been asleep most of the time with My.
- I haven't had a chance to bother anybody. Haven't I, MoominTroll?
Uhh huh.
- Dad, what does "uhh huh" mean?
That finally I can hear my thoughts again.
- When My is gone.
Go on, knock on the door, Thingumy.
- What if somebody comes and starts to yell?
Maybe they won't open it at all. Go now.
Knock.
- Excuse me?
What got into them? Don't forget your suitcase.
What should we do? What what what?
- I won't bite. I'm a local policeman and have served in Moomin Valley for ages.
A policeman! We're not thieves! We're not thieves!
Has somebody accused you to be?
- Hasn't anyone? Didn't you come to arrest us?
Of course not. I'm going to greet the Moomins.
This suitcase is ours.
- Has anybody claimed otherwise? Take it.
Ah, you are finally here.
Are they your guests?
- I guess so. And they have a suitcase so I suppose they are staying a while. Fun!
Is that okay for you?
- Of course. I am MoominMamma.
I am Thingumy and this is Bob.
- Welcome. Step in and be at home.
I think we can stay... Let's hide the suitcase.
They really are weird.
- Yes they are.
How can I help you today?
- Um, I heard Mymble is back...
Yes she is.
- Is she coming here?
No, she left to go home with My a little while ago.
- Well okay, as a policeman I have to check every small detail.
Well bye then MoominMamma.
He has a crush on Mymble.
- But does Mymble have a crush on him?
I don't know.
- What are the guests doing?
-- Looking scared...
I have emptied the drawers for you.
- Thank you.
Where should we put the suitcase?
- Into a drawer?
It can easily be hid in here.
- Oh look, they have made such cute beds for us!
Let's hide the suitcase in a drawer.
We have to be careful...
- I like the Moomins. They don't scream.
We still have to be careful...
Peculiar guests like our house but the two are exceptionally peculiar...
- Yes they're from the north.
And their names are Thingumy and Bob.
- How about the suitcase?
They seem like refugees to me.
- Who try to avoid contact with the police.
Do you want to see them?
- Well I guess so.
Oh there you are.
- What are they doing?
No idea. There was only snoring coming from their room.
- We think that they are refugees.
I wonder what's in the suitcase?
- Money?
Or state secrets...
- Maybe they are arsonists. Let's hide the matches.
The public enemies number 1 and 2. They don't look like it though.
Would you like to have some tea, Snufkin and Sniff?
- Thank you.
-- Cookies too, thanks.
Oh no, the suitcase is gone! What am I going to do now?
You got up already?
- Oh you were under the bed.
It's the safest place.
- Something is going to happen soon...
What?
- It woke me up. I feel it's coming.
It can't possibly know we're here...
- Yes it can, and it will come tonight!
Well it's really windy out there.
- And suddenly really chilly too.
Hey, did you sleep well? Come join us.
- There you are!
This is Sniff and Snufkin. You don't have to be afraid of them.
What's wrong?
It's coming!
- Yes it is!
Who's coming?
- The Groke!
The Groke?!
- It's horrible!
-- Horrible?
The Groke?
- Do you know about it?
I haven't seen it but it's a terrifying monster.
- Terrifying monster?
And it's following you?
- Yes! It will be here soon!
Don't be afraid. The Groke won't be arguing with me.
- It doesn't? It won't!
But if it's a monster...
- Monster or not, guests will always be safe in Moomin House.
You two go to your room and lock all the doors.
- Thank you MoominPappa.
No one will pass without me saying so.
- No!
Grab your guns, dear family!
Does anyone want more tea?
What's wrong?
- A monster will attack us, MoominMamma.
Dear God!
- MoominMamma, grab your pan in case there is a fight.
I wonder if everyone has a good weapon.
Oh, it's midnight.
- There is no stupid monster...
I sure hope not.
It's coming! It's here!
- Very close!
Nonsense! I will go home. We can't stay up all night.
- Okay.
I'll go now so you know.
- Watch your back.
Use open roads.
- You're trying to scare me, but I don't scare that easily.
It's here!
- No it's not! There are no monsters. A sudden wind blew out the candles!
There's nothing out there...
- Good, so nothing stops you from going home.
Admit that no monsters exist. You were just scaring me. Nonsense!
No one to be seen.
Don't scramble like that.
- It's here! It's here!
Where?
- Right there! Behind the door!
No, no, don't open the door!
Forward!
No one.
- No one? Are you sure?
Yea right, no one. We scared it away!
- There it is!
Groke, we would be happy if you would go home.
You make our guests nervous.
- You froze my flowers!
-- Leave Mom's flowers alone!
You must leave before I count to ten. One, Two, Three...
Are you okay?
- Look at the ground...
Icy.
I'll be back!
- The voice of The Groke...
Yuck, it's cold.
- Yes, it is.
It won't be back tonight.
- Let's go in and drink something warm.
And it didn't come back, but why was it sneaking around the Moomin House in the first place? And will it come back when everyone is asleep?