Due to last night's thrill Sniff decided to stay overnight at the Moomin house.
Snufkin retired, as usual, to his tent.
Do you remember what had happened?
The gruesome Groke had followed Thingumy and Bob and everything around the Groke froze.
For Moomintroll the horrors of last night were not yet over.
Help! The Groke is chasing me!
Don't come! Leave me alone!
Huh? Why am I laying on the floor?
Good morning Mom!
- Good morning! Has Sniff woken up yet?
Never in a million years.
Where are they?
- In their room still. Those poor things.
Is Dad still sleeping too?
- No. Dad is outside in the yard.
Dad! What are you doing?
- The roses are dead.
- How in the world?
These are The Groke's acts from last night.
The ground around The Groke froze but I wouldn't have believed the flowers would die too.
I wish we could have captured him in an ice cellar.
I dreamed that the Groke was chasing me.
- Don't you worry. I think the Groke is looking for Thingumy and Bob.
At least they're not hiding from the fist of the law.
- That might be even more desirable for them.
Aren't Thingumy and Bob coming down?
- They wanted to have breakfast in their room.
Well, what did they tell you? Why is the nasty Groke chasing them?
- Well, they didn't tell me. They just seemed terrified.
We have to find out.
Moominmamma, bring them breakfast and dig their secrets out.
Who's there?
- It's just me. I'm bringing you breakfast.
You may come in.
Well? What did they tell you?
- The Groke seems to be after their suitcase and not them.
I wonder what those lilliputians are hiding in their suitcase!
And it seems to be that the suitcase previously belonged to the Groke.
Have they stolen it from the Groke?
- That matter didn't become clear. They were very reticent about it.
This is going too far!
- Who knows if we are taking care of dangerous criminals in our home!
Let's ask the Groke!
- Shh! That is out of the question.
We don't want the Groke back here, do we?
- Let's ask the police to ask the Groke.
Let's not bring police into this.
- What should we do then?!
- Don't you shout at me there!
Wait for them to open their mouths. If you just pretend to be unconcerned they shall soon reveal their secrets.
They didn't tell anything to Dad and just tiny bit to Mom.
We need a woman, but rather someone in the same age group as Thingumy and Bob.
- Of course.
Snorkmaiden! Where are you headed?
- To the Moomin house.
- I'm coming with you!
I thought you lived there.
- Not anymore! My sister came back home yesterday.
How is she?
- She's bossing around and snoring!
Where are you going?
- To see you.
And I was coming to see you.
- And me too.
I brought you a gift.
- A gift?
- Yes, and it's very beautiful.
What is it?
- You cannot break or loose it.
Of course not.
Here you are.
- Thank you.
Open it.
Oh, what a beautiful seashell.
I was roaming around the beach purposely for you.
Look, you can use it as a mirror.
- True, oh thank you!
I'm giving my heart to your tender care.
I will caress it. This seashell will always remind me of you.
- Oh Moomintroll.
I will give the seashell a kiss every time I go to bed.
It shall be my most precious gift!
- Besides me.
So I'm supposed to go for a walk with Thingumy and Bob?
- Yes, and don't rush them at all.
They can cry against my shoulder.
- We need to get them to talk.
Oh I feel so important and nervous...
- Here, have some tea.
- Thank you.
My, you're not needed here.
- I will dig up their secrets with force if needed!
We are not detectives. We will only speak with them.
- And dig up their secrets! I will be totally silent.
Have you ever tried to be silent?
- Maybe not. I wonder if I should try. I will come with Snorkmaiden!
We need a tender and understanding woman here.
- But I am! In a nutshell!
Are you ready?
- I think so.
It's Moomintroll. I have something to say to you.
This is Snorkmaiden. A tender and understanding girl.
- Hello! Nice to meet you and your friend.
Snorkmaiden wants to talk with you. Will you let her in?
Well, if she necessarily wants. Come on in then.
Shaped precisely like a heart. And so beautiful! I have never seen anything like it.
Do you want something similar?
- No! Seashells like this are one in a million.
Keep it in your purse.
Snorkmaiden will certainly succeed.
- Yeah, they seemed to like her.
The Groke is coming tonight, I can feel it in my bones.
- You're right.
If we only could find out why the Groke is after them.
If that monster comes every night Mom will lose all her flowers.
- Look!
They're going outside.
- Good, good!
We need to stop My before she ruins everything.
I will never forgive you if you get yourself into this!
- Don't you intervene in this.
Let's have Snorkmaiden handle this.
- But I'm just shadowing them!
So Snorkmaiden took them for a walk. Where are they now?
I can't hear a word what they are saying.
- Me neither. We need to get closer.
- Then they'll spot us.
I'm the only one who is small enough to get close enough.
- Don't go! You'll make Snorkmaiden nervous.
You're the one making her nervous!
Well then, may I additionally ask...
- You may!
Does that suitcase belong to you or the Groke?
- Yes it does.
I shall try once more... To whom does that suitcase belong to?
- It's ours!
But to you told Moominmamma that the suitcase belongs to the Groke.
- Yes, it does!
May I ask the same thing once more?
- Ask away!
About that suitcase... How is it? Do you own the suitcase?
- No we don't! - Yes we do!
"Don't rush them" says Moomintroll...
- What's wrong?!
Excuse me, but may I ask once more?
- As many times as you like.
Oh thank you! I'll ask for the last time. Answer truthfully...
That suitcase... - Yes?
...that you have... - Yes?
...is it yours? - It is!
So it's not the Groke's?
- No it's not the Groke's!
At last! Thank the heavens, thank you!
- Thank the heavens, thank you!
Snorkmaiden had it hard.
- I would've said boo and they would've coughed up their secrets.
- Of that I'm sure!
Snorkmaiden is nice!
- All the people in the Moomin house are nice!
Do you think they'd want to keep us forever?
- Of course, if we can deal with the Groke!
- Yeah, if we can deal with the Groke!
I won over their trust and now we're good friends.
Who wouldn't be your friend?
Thank you. It wasn't very easy though. They tend to mess things up.
I feel like I'm the only one who doesn't mess things up!
I didn't find out much.
- I should have been handling it!
Snorkmaiden, what did you find out then?
- Well, firstly, the suitcase seems to belong to them.
Why does the Groke then...
- Stop rushing!
The content, on the other hand, belongs to the Groke.
Good heavens. This is a complicated case.
Hey, what's inside the suitcase?
- They wouldn't tell, just that it's the most beautiful thing in the world.
In the whole world?
- The most beautiful thing?
- Ugh! This is so complicated. They don't really look like thieves.
I think we still need to drive the Groke away.
- I don't understand how the Groke can own the most beautiful thing in the world.
Thingumy and Bob told me that the Groke just happens to own it.
The Groke might have stolen the content of the suitcase himself.
- Dear heavens.
Thingumy and Bob are awfully afraid of the Groke's vengeance.
But they still won't give up the content of the suitcase.
- Quite a mess!
The Groke will surely come tonight. What are we going to do?
- The same as last night!
If the content of the suitcase belongs to the Groke we can't just drive it away.
I doubt the Groke will leave as easily this time. If it stays we could be facing an everlasting winter.
I will cover my petunias, just in case. Are you staying here?
- I will go to Snork.
- I'm going home!
But Snufkin stays. Don't look so gloomy. I have a plan!
What kind of a plan?
- Just one... You'll see.
The Groke is coming! It's already close!
- Maybe Moominpappa will drive it away.
Your turn, My.
- I know, I know. If you don't have an ace of clubs...
Hm, the Groke's coming now.
- Just as I was about to win!
Go under the table, this might become dangerous!
- Crazy, how can I whack with the rolling pin from under the table?
Is the Groke here already?
- Yeah, at the same spot as yesterday.
I'll go and stomp it's feet!
- I'll go first. All of you stay behind me.
Moominmamma!
- Yes darling?
You said you have a plan. Wouldn't this be the time for it?
Listen, Groke. We wan't to talk with you. We know you have come back to collect belongings that Thingumy and Bob have stolen from you, isn't that so?
Would you sell your belonging to them?
Or would you give it for free?
I have beautiful items in my purse. Could we trade?
What do you think about this medallion?
Oh, you don't like it?
What about this?
Or this?
Can't you settle with anything? You can choose anything from my purse, except the aspirins.
Do you mean this?
Or this?
Oh dear, this isn't mine actually. Moomintroll, can I give the seashell?
Mom! Are you hurt?
- No. My hand just suddenly froze.
Now that you have the seashell promise to never return.
Don't you dare come back!
Huh, that was close. Moominmamma had her senses. Thank you Mamma!
I'm sorry Moomintroll. I didn't remember your seashell was in my purse.
- It's okay, Mom.
I wonder what Snorkmaiden thinks? You promised to give the seashell a kiss every night or something else as stupid.
Mom did the right thing. Besides, I won't tell Snorkmaiden.
Goof. The truth will always come out. From now on I will always tell the truth.
Moomintroll look, I found one!
- It's very similar but mine was a lot bigger.
- Oh was it a lot bigger?
Moomintroll had to find a seashell that would look exactly like the one Snorkmaiden had given him.
Here it is! Here it is! I found it!
Look! It's precisely the same!
It was a miracle! But miracles do happen in Moomin Valley.