Oh, sorry Moominmamma!
- We were so clumsy.
Oh, it's alright.
Hey, you dropped this!
Thank you. Are you going out now?
Oh yes, now that the Groke is gone!
- Have fun!
Thingumy and Bob really seemed to make themselves at home in Moomin House.
They are very small and the only ones who can find dropped pencils around the floor.
Hey! This looks like an especially secret place!
- Oh yes, nobody can't find it here!
Let's bring the suitcase right here.
- Are you sure we couldn't just keep it in our room?
What if someone goes into the room when we are somewhere else? What then?
The Moomins are not going to go there and sneak around. They are nice.
Yeah but what about guests? The Moomins will let anyone inside the house. Anyone!
Snorkmaiden!
You lied to me.
What do you mean?
- Moomintroll still has the shell I gave to him.
That's impossible. Moominmamma gave that to Groke. I saw it!
I saw that Moomintroll still has the shell.
But was that same one?
Of course it was! I know it!
Weird. Moominmamma really did give it to the Groke...
Oh well, I'm going to see Moomintroll right away.  Are you coming?
Coming! Coming! I need to find out the truth!
We will dig it out.
- The whole thing seems really strange...
That's true.
Mymble and I went to beach yesterday.
- So what?
We found an exciting object. Do you remember all that stuff we found after the storm?
Of course I do! It was only couple of weeks ago.
And do you remember that wooden sculpture Snufkin found?
- Yes I remember.
Moomintroll totally fell in love with that thing!
- Don't remind me of it...
It's here now.
- No it's not!
You have to remember that nowadays I speak the truth and only the truth.
It wasn't changed at all. It was as beautiful as before.
Are you sure it was the same?
Of course it is! Beauty without arms and a butt.
That's true. Just a legless wooden doll!
Beautiful chick with big eyes! Moomintroll is in love with that!
Is it still at the beach?
I think so. Unless someone has found it already.
My, do you think that waves could wash that thing away?
I don't know, but those waves did bring it to the beach.
If Moomintroll finds that statue he will save it.
- Yeah.
He will bring it to his room...
Nah, it can't fit through the door.
He will figure something out...
- No! It can't fit!
Oh well, I can't foretell that.
And then he will sit and watch that statue with a stupid expression on his face! That damned!
Snorkmaiden! Weren't you supposed to go to the Moomin House?
Yeah I was. But I just remembered something important!
Route is clear.
You are not going to leave, are you?
No! We just, just...
Then why do you have that suitcase?
Umm, will you help us carrying it?
- Gladly.
Thank you, Moomintroll.
- Don't worry, this is just a small favour.
We are going to take it from here to a secret place.
- Suitcase isn't heavy.
Oh, sorry! A secret place isn't really secret if I have seen it... I'll leave.
Don't tell anyone about this!
- Of course not.
What are you doing up there?
What does it look like? I'm coming down!
No you can't! You are way too small for that!
- I'll show you that I'm not!
Moomintroll, I would like to ask you something
- Ask away.
Moominmamma gave your shell to the Groke, didn't she?
- Yes she did.
Then you can't have it because the Groke took it!
I still have it.
But that's not possible in any way!
We gave the Groke a different shell.
- That's a lie! No you didn't!
Okay then. But for Snorkmaiden's sake I will say it was a different shell.
That is complicated. Tell me the truth!
It is a secret.
- I wanna know!
If you tell me that secret I'll tell you mine.
- And what is that?
It is a secret in a Little My way.
Yeah but what is it?
- You tell first.
No, you tell first.
Let's start telling at the same time.
- Okay, let's do that.
One, two, three...
When I gave the shell to Groke I knew I was going to get trouble and didn't know what to do...
- I was at the beach yesterday with Mymble and we found that woman shaped figurehead.
What?! That wooden woman?
- Where the cave begins.
Hey, you didn't tell your secret!
- Later!
Unfair! Tell it right now!
What is Moomintroll doing over there?
- Is he looking for seashells again?
Maybe not seashells, but he is looking for something.
- He seems to have lost something important.
How far do we have to go?
- As far as you can manage to row.
The beach is so far away!
- This old lady needs to be taken so far away that she never comes back! Is that clear?
This is far enough already...
- There are still ocean currents! Row it far away, far away...
He looks sad.
- Let's make him happy!
There is only one way.
- You are right.
Thingumy and Bob.
- You look so sad that we thought that we could try to make you happier, okay?
Is that okay with you?
- It's okay, but you don't have to.
We are going to show you what is in our suitcase!
- Ooh!
Do you want to see it? It's really beautiful!
Of course I want to see it!
Do you need help?
- No. We can handle this!
Thank you for your help.
Now we are going to open suitcase.
- We are going to open in one, two, three!
Oooh, by my tail!
Do you like it?
- Oh do I like it?
You are not sad anymore, are you?
- No.
Well that's funny.
- Really funny.
What a ruby! How it changes its colours!
From warm red to sapphire blue then pink. Like a flame that flares over and over again and suddenly it has the nuance of a black tulip.
Hmm, maybe that is the king ruby.
- It has to be!
It is the one which the magician is looking for while riding on his panther.
- Oy!
He might be somewhere far away right now looking for that ruby but he will come back to Moomin Valley one day.
First Groke and now a magician... Poor little things!
It wasn't even a week before there was a terrible accident at Moomin Valley like lightning from a clear sky.
It's not in the bedroom either.
That's weird. Where was the last place you saw it?
- Somewhere here...
Maybe it is in the garden.
I haven't been outside all day.
That's right, Moominmamma's purse went missing. In the purse were dry socks, wire, painkillers, and a hand knife for making bark boats.
What is the matter?
- My purse is missing and I feel so helpless.
Will I get a reward if I find it?
Definitely. And I will arrange a big party with cakes and everything and no one has to take an evening bath or go to sleep early!
I'll find that bag!
- No, I will!
Your purse definitely isn't in the cellar.
That's great, dear Snork. I haven't been in a cellar for a day anyway, though.
Word was spreading and soon everyone was looking for Moominmamma's purse.
Well, there are a lot of people.
- What are they looking for?
What is everybody searching for?
- My purse.
That one with cute little pockets?
- The very same.
You can just go and play.
It is so comfortable to sleep inside Moominmamma's purse!
Moominmamma seems so sad.
- Maybe we should give it back.
You found it! The purse is found! Thingumy and Bob found Moominmamma's purse!
Oh thank you so much! Where did you find it?
Oh, just somewhere in the bush. Under the big birch.
- Moominmamma's purse is so pretty!
In honor of finding the purse we will have a big party tonight!
As you know, this party has been arranged because Moominmamma's purse was found. Thank you to everyone who was looking for it!
I'll propose a toast for our heroes Thingumy and Bob!
Without that purse there would be something missing in Moomin Valley. Cheers!
Moomintroll has something to say to you.
Um, we are glad that my mother's purse was found and, umm, thank you.
As a thank you for this great party, Thingumy and Bob have decided to show us what is in their mysterious suitcase!
We have a unique opportunity for this. Okay, Thingumy and Bob, are you ready?
Ready?
- Ready! One, two, three!
How wonderful!
How could Groke trade such a jewel for a seashell?
It has to be the king ruby.
The King ruby!
Magician!
The ruby that I have sworn to find!
Keep your fingers away! The ruby is ours!
- Go away you mean magician!
That ruby is my property.
No it's not! The Groke traded that for a heart shaped seashell with Thingumy and Bob!
Oh? For a heart shape seashell?
- Oh well.
The Groke gave that ruby to these two. I witnessed it with my own eyes.
I have been searching for this ruby for 300 years.
That is sad. But it's not yours.
Would you change that ruby for two large diamonds?
- No way!
I can't take the ruby by force. This really starts to get to my nerves.
Would the magician like a mug of punch?
- Thank you. I haven't had punch for 85 years.
Ah, Quince.
- There is that too.
Would you like to have more?
- Thank you, that was enough. Magicians are not big drinkers.
This is a great party and good punch. I will do magic to please you.
I'll show you magic. You can have three wishes. Please make wishes. Please form a single line to make your wishes.
What now? Are you afraid? You seem too old to be afraid.
Well I'm not afraid. Oh yes, I broke a shovel that I borrowed from Moominpappa. I wish to have a shovel!
Dear Hemulin, not those kind of wishes!
I would like to have a new shovel.
- Then that is what you will get.
Thank you very much!
Thank you for lending this.
Next!
- Sorry but...
What can I do for you, young lady?
- It could be little difficult...
Even for me?
Is that what you want?
- Yes
Close your eyes.
Your wish has come true, little lady.
Oh my gosh!
- Snorkmaiden!
I wished to have similar eyes as that legless lady that you find so beautiful.
You changed totally!
- Give me a mirror quickly!
Pretty beautiful, actually.
Oh, terrible!
Can I have my old eyes back?
- I'm sorry, only one wish per person.
Mister Magician, can I make a wish now?
- Please. Golden carriage, crystal goblet, anything!
I would definitely wish for a sack full of gold coins!
- Moomintroll wishes.
Well, ask a two sacks of coins and then I could have the other one. What do you say?
I have already made my decision.
Please, could you be so nice and return Snorkmaiden's eyes back to the way they were?
She sees perfectly with those already! Farewell, golden coins.
Your wish has been heard. And granted.
Well, look!
You should have thought before wishing.
- Oh my Moomintroll!
Ummm, Magician?
- What?
If you can make magic that way, why don't you wish yourself a ruby?
- I can't. I can only do magic for others.
Is it okay then if we wish for something together for you?
- That would probably be okay.
Let us wish!
- Okay then.
We wish a similar ruby for you!
- Your wish will be granted.
It is for you!
- Thank you, thank you.
And that is how the Magician's 300 year search was finished. And there had never been a party as cheerful in Moomin Valley before.
Everybody was happy. Except maybe Nipsu who wanted sack full of gold coins.