Well, hurry up! That over there is the Moomin House!
On that day it started to rain in the early afternoon.
Everyone was shivering inside when Too-Ticky came.
Good evening, Moomintroll.
- Hi, come in!
Mother, Too-Ticky is here.
Ninny, please come in.
Aren't you alone?
- No. I have Ninny with me.
Ninny?
Come in!
There's nobody out there...
- Believe me, she's there even if you don't see her.
Is she?
- Yes. She is just really shy.
I'll leave the door open so you can come in when you are ready.
She's going to get wet.
- Maybe. It doesn't matter if you are invisible.
Oh, Too-Ticky! Fun!
What is everybody staring at?
You know that if someone gets very badly scared they can turn invisible, right?
The Aunt has taken care of Ninny out of obligation.
The Aunt doesn't like her at all. She is behaving badly.
The Aunt doesn't get angry or yell. You would understand that.
She's just ice cold and sarcastic. It's terrible. Just terrible.
What does sarcastic mean?
Well, think if you fall and land in the middle of a coffee table. What would your mother do?
She would ask if I got hurt.
This Aunt would say: "This may be dancing to you but don't dance in the food." That's sarcasm.
That's nasty.
She was really sarcastic. All day, every day.
So eventually Ninny started to fade away until last Friday when she disappeared entirely.
That's terrible!
The aunt gave Ninny to me because she said she cannot take care of invisible relatives.
So what did you do with the Aunt? Did you smack her?
That doesn't work with sarcastic people.
I took Ninny and brought her here so you would make her visible again.
Very flattering, but...
- If someone can do it Moominmamma can. And Moomintroll can play with her.
Too-Ticky, does Ninny speak?
- No, unfortunately not.
Oh dear.
- What can we play then? She will be invincible if we play hide-and-seek.
The aunt put a bell on her neck. You will hear where she goes.
Oh the door opened.
- It must be Ninny!
Come out from the rain, Ninny.
Moomin House is your new home. The Moomins are very kind.
This is Moominpappa, this is Moominmamma and this is--
- Snorkmaiden, My, Sniff and Moomintroll.
We're just having tea. Would you like to have some if you can drink?
I'll bring you juice.
I would like to see how the juice moves inside of her. This way, Ninny.
Well that's all. Unfortunately I can't tell you more about her. You'll be fine.
- It's going to be okay.
Here you go, Ninny.
Well, I'll be going now. There are lots of things to do at home. I'll come by every now and then to see how you are doing.
Sounds like a plan.
What now?
- It just came to my mind, did you have some extra visitors here?
Yes we had. Thingummy and Bob. They moved out last week.
- Yea, that's good.
You drank it all! Do you want some more?
I hope it was good.
Ninny, will you come upstairs with me? The bell is pretty.
This is your room.
I'll leave some juice on the night table so you can drink whenever you want.
Are you ready to go to bed?
Just tuck yourself in. Ninny, if you start feeling lonely during the night you can come and wake me up.
Well then, ring your bell.
Good night.
Is she asleep?
- Yes.
Maybe we can find a cure for her from your grandmothers notebook, called "Guaranteed Home Medicine".
I wonder if there is a medicine for invisibility. I don't remember but we can check.
I believe there is a medicine.
I know that, my darling. I will go and check.
I want to see Ninny.
There it is. Bad eye... Depression... Limp tail...
Ah here it is!
The recipe was written at the end of the notebook.
It was the right one because it said: "The cure is if someone starts being foggy and difficult to see."
I hope it works.
Grandmother's recipes always work.
Yes, I know. I wonder if she is still asleep.
Look! I can see her shoes!
Moominpappa!
Morning, My.
Is she up yet?
- Yes, yes.
Where is she? I hope she hasn't eaten yet!
I think she is in the dining hall.
Where is she?
Be quiet! Ninny is taking medicine.
One sip, for Moomintroll.
There you go. It should activate in 2 hours.
Her shoes are floating!
- Yes, her shoes are visible now.
Look! They look funny!
- She has beautiful feet.
I doubt Moominmamma's medicines take effect that fast.
You must look ugly because you prefer to be invisible.
Don't mind Little My, she always talks like that.
I still can't see how the food flows inside of her.
What shall we do?
Go pick mushrooms.
- Boring. I never find any.
I do. Ninny, shall we go?
Decided. Who will pick up the most?
You need to tell me which mushrooms are edible.
We will.
Father! Father! Look! Her shoes are visible!
Moominmamma's medicines are known for their effectiveness.
It can't be the medicine.
I think the medicine took effect faster because of a missing body.
Or because the aunt is far away.
Could be.
Mother! We will take Ninny to pick mushrooms.
Wonderful.
Morning!
Where is she?
Awesome! You're good at this!
Lots of mushrooms!
I only have half.
How many have you got, Moomintroll?
4 times as much as I have!
You have never picked up so many before.
There is something rotten in here...
Oh, they were Ninny's mushrooms!
- Yea, they were.
The awful aunt never let her go mushroom picking so she has the drive now.
But I bet she only had permission to carry a basket.
How terrible! How terrible!
Stinky.
What does he want?
Shall I bite him?
We haven't seen in a long time!
- And I wouldn't care. Last time you dunked my bathing suit in glue!
That was funny!
How is the basket floating?
I don't want to be rude but I won't tell.
I wonder what you could do if you were invisible.
Ninny, I'll take your basket. Let's go.
Come on, Ninny!
Hey! Is Ninny your real name or the species?
Stinky! Stop right now! You'll scare her!
Is she a female? Ninny, right? That's a nerdy name.
Beware, Stinky.
What is it now?
Do not pick on Ninny or I'll get mad.
Without the shoes she would be a good bank robber.
Don't even think about it. She's going to turn visible soon. Yesterday we started to see her feet.
And now they are fading again.
Stinky! It was you!
Tell Moominmamma and Moominpappa she will be a good bank robber!
She won't do that! Besides, we're going to make her visible!
She has already taken mother's magical medicine!
Who's is this?
Me and My's.
Oh dear, very beautiful.
We didn't find much because Ninny picked up most of the mushrooms.
It doesn't matter if there aren't many, but you can't eat these mushrooms.
This one is poisonous.
And this is Fly Amanita.
Be wary of these two mushrooms.
I think these are Moomintroll and Sniff's mushrooms.
We did not pick poisonous mushrooms.
You have a little less, but this one is a Panther Fly Amanita.
And what about this?
Both of you have poisonous mushrooms.
But Ninny has no poisonous mushrooms in her basket.
How has she picked up so many by herself?
Ninny, come here. Where are you?
Moominmamma, let's make a warrant for Ninny.
Ninny, I would say this is a beautiful mushroom basket.
Hey, I can see her feet!
Great, Ninny! Soon we will see your face too!
That won't take long. Don't worry about Stinky. He is just nasty.
"Don't think sad things." That's my motto.
And mine is "Bite the person who picks on you."
If someone is so great picking mushrooms they deserve to get fully visible.
Look! We can see her legs!
Ninny, that's progression!
- Congratulations. I can't wait to see you.
Soon it will happen but I don't think grey suits you.
Sleep as long as you wish.
Good night, Ninny.
Where is Mamma?
What on earth are you doing? Do you know what time it is?
How do you like this?
It's very pretty.
It's nice to have somebody in the house who uses clothes. I wonder how it will look on her.
What is this?
- A hair band.
Morning, Moominpappa!
Morning. You're early.
Where is Ninny?
- Still asleep.
You're up early.
How much of her is visible?
- Come and see.
It's like opening a present.
A row of presents. Every day a new one.
- Exactly.
I think this is much more exciting.
Did I hear a door?
- She's awake!
I hope she saw the dress I put out for her.
The dress looks fine.
Now you know which way to talk.
Yes, right!
Thank you for everything.
She can talk!
Even if they didn't see her face yet it was a relief to hear her talking.
It feels silly to talk to somebody who doesn't respond and then you're more likely to say something stupid.