Hey! Where is Ninny?
Ninny told us she wants to play with us.
Ninny, come have fun with us!
Let's go already.
Because of her ironical Aunt, the invisible Ninny could now be seen up to her neck, but the head refused to appear even though Moominmamma poured grandma's medicine on her.
Look, an invisible child.
- I wonder what she looks like?
Good morning everyone!
- You little lumpsucker! It's past 12PM!
We are going to play hide and seek in the forest.
- Wonderful. How is it going, Ninny?
-- Good.
This is dumb, if I was able to see you, I wouldn't have to ask.
- For your part, you look always dumb.
This place is big for hide and seek.
The bigger it is the more exciting it'll be.
Let's, however, follow this new rule...
- Which one?
That you can't change your hiding spot in the middle of the game. Do you get it Ninny?
Sniff, you'll be the first one to count.
- Why is it always me?
We have to practice because Ninny is with us.
There's no need to practice playing hide and seek.
Look, Ninny has never played hide and seek.
- Oh! She hasn't?
Ninny has never played hide and seek, and nothing else either.
Not even when she was visible?
- No...
Oh dear.
Is it okay that you stay and be the seeker?
- I won't.
Alright then, I'll stay.
I'll slowly count to 10 so that you have time to hide.
1... 2...
Go hide quickly, Ninny!
3...
4!
Go further!
5...
6...
7...
8...
9...
Hey, Ninny! Don't be afraid of me. Go hide behind that bush.
- 10!
I'll start to search!
- Thank you.
I found you Sniff!
My has been found!
I wonder where Ninny has hid?
I found you! You had a good hiding spot but I saw your bow.
Only Snorkmaiden left but she's never hard to find.
Snorkmaiden wants to be found.
- I found Snorkmaiden!
3...
4...
5...
- This is my bush!
6...
7...
Hey Ninny, I know a good spot for you, they'll never find you there!
The opening is a bit tight, but the cavern widens further in.
Hurry up or Sniff will find you!
There you go! Now when you stay there until tomorrow you'll turn entirely invisible!
I want out!
- Tomorrow we'll go rob the bank together!
I don't want to!
Let me out!
You'll get half... Ehm, a quarter of the loot!
It was such a good idea to bring Ninny here.
- Good to hear you think so, Too-ticky.
You people are so extraordinary that your peculiar behaviour might turn Ninny back visible again and of course you are very friendly!
Well thank you, I guess we should be flattered.
- Absolutely.
By the way, Ninny is speaking already. Her voice is very delicate though.
- Has her voice always been like that?
Who knows, that might be.
Otherwise many people get by well without using their heads.
It's nice that Ninny has playmates. She hasn't had those before at all!
But... I don't think she knows how to play.
I think that some kind of shock would do her good.
I found you!
- Ugh, there were spikes in the bush anyway.
Well I was found the last.
- Ninny is still missing.
-- Really?
You hid in the same bush as Ninny?
Well, Ninny is very skilled.
Oh well, maybe Ninny is lost.
I've been looking everywhere but she's gone invisible again and that's why I can't find her.
Sniff is in serious trouble.
I wonder where Ninny might be?
- I don't know, I haven't seen her.
Ninny, come out! We're going home!
Ninny! Ninny!
- Where on the earth is she?
Your job is to find her.
- Not anymore when we've stopped playing the game!
I think we have to find Ninny. Let's all help look for her.
Ohoy, Ninny, come out! The game is over!
Ninny! We're going home to drink juice and eat cookies!
Ninny! Ninny! Ninny, where are you?
We weren't supposed to go this far to hide.
- Listen! Maybe Ninny really is lost.
Ninny! Ninny! Come out!
Ninny!
- Help me, I'm here!
Huh? Did you hear something?
- Maybe.
I'm here!
Ninny's voice!
It's coming from a close range.
Ninny, where are you?
Here! Inside the rocks!
Ninny can't be far!
- Let's hurry
Ninny! I couldn't hear what you said! Where are you?
I am here! Here!
Getting hotter, hotter... Say it louder!
- Inside the rocks!
Say it once more!
- Here inside the rocks!
There!
Oh my, I have never yelled so loud...
Ninny, are you trapped behind this rock?
I am. Stinky closed the opening.
We'll get you out! Let's move the boulder.
Are you okay?
- I am, Moomintroll. Thank you.
Your voice is stronger.
- Returned.
-- Is that so?
Take my hand and I'll pull you out.
- I'm coming.
What has happened?
- Ninny was inside the hole of this rock.
Great! Ninny found an excellent hiding place!
Did I say something funny?
Nifty to think about Ninny robbing a bank.
I guess...
- Stinky was quite the shock to Ninny. But she didn't turn invisible after all and her voice is a lot louder now.
Ninny yelled as loud as she could.
- Did you really yell that loud?
I did. Moomintroll told me to yell so he could hear where I was.
And loud you yelled.
- Good Ninny! Those who speak up loudly are usually also seen well. Remember that!
Yell! I want to see you.
Good thinking, and try to get angry too! Too-Ticky would be delighted if you could turn visible again.
Get angry to Stinky!
- Stinky is so horrible!
He should not be! He better watch his back!
Stinky! Wait!
You will not catch me!
Stinky! I need to speak with you!
I have nothing to say to you!
Are you hurt?
Stinky, you will not get away!
- The woods are my homefield! You will not catch me here!
You can't do this to me!
- We'll do the same to you as what you did to Ninny.
I needed Ninny's help.
- She didn't want to help!
I shut her down here so she could change her mind.
And would be so shocked that she would turn entirely invisible!
My plan demanded her being invisible. Let me out!
Not a chance. Till tomorrow!
You crooks! You're doing this out of spite!
This will be remembered!
In spite of all, Ninny's face was still invisible.
Then, around 10 days later...
Nails bounce out on a weather like this!
I've never seen anyone stare at the sea like that.
I guess Ninny has never seen the ocean.
Well, now she's weeping.
Ninny, what's wrong?
- The ocean is too big, way too big.
You don't have to go to the ocean, do you?
Hey, Moominmamma!
- Yes?
What's wrong with Ninny?
There's nothing wrong with her. She's just astonished about the size of the ocean.
Well, there is an awful lot of water in the ocean...
Me on the other hand, I haven't been astonished or nervous of anything for weeks.
Mom is bored.
- Seems so.
Mom is never bored.
- Now she clearly is! She wishes that something surprising would happen.
You think so?
- We have to set up a surprise for her.
What kind of a surprise?
- So that she's really surprised!
Dad, don't tell me you're going to push her into the ocean?
- What would be a better surprise?
But the water is freezing.
- When we were young the water was never too cold for us!
Did you push each other into the ocean?
- All the time!
Dad?
- What?
-- Nothing...
Don't worry, your Mother will think it's very funny.
You can't!
Don't you dare to push Moominmamma into the ocean!
Let me explain!
There's nothing to explain you meany! Moominmamma would get drenched!
You can't do it!
Ninny!
Ninny is visible!
How fun!
Finally we can see Ninny!
Pappa, did something happen?
- Not really... She's the most wicked and sharp toothed child I've ever seen.
I finally turned visible!
Yeah, and you won't disappear again!
Not ever!
Brisk girl, and has seemingly good teeth.
Ninny, I'm so happy!
Ninny!
Mamma!
I'm happy too.
Don't laugh at me you wretched brat, saw-toothed monster!
What is so funny?
Did Ninny really laugh?
You have truly changed her.
- Indeed. She's almost as bad as Little My.
I have never heard Ninny laugh, but the best thing is still that she has turned back visible.
Ninny!
- Too-Ticky!
And so Too-Ticky took Ninny as she had brought her, but now Ninny was visible and was anything but shy.
Ninny was said to be ready for anything, except going back to her Aunt.