Snorkmaiden is running like the Groke was after her,
probably the fastest she had ever run.
What is going on?
Moomintroll!
Moominpappa, help!
Calm down, and tell what is the matter.
My brother is going to jump off the ledge.
Snork?
- I offended him.
He said he is going to jump anyway. Moomintroll you need to stop him!
Snorkmaiden, how can I help you?
Snork can't be allowed to jump off the southern ledge.
- He is that type of a person!
Snork is going to do a test flight.
- Oh my God!
Snorkmaiden, do you mean that your brother's flight apparatus is finally ready?
Oh no, it's probably just a blueprint.
Well that is something anyway.
He has built model parts for his future flight gadgets wings, but in my opinion they seem way too weak to keep him in the air.
They could never keep him in the air. Never!
Alrighty, and now Snork is going to see how his flight gadget's wings are going to work.
You have to stop his experiment!
- Stop him, Dad.
Did you say southern hill?
- Yes I did. It is steepest and highest.
Then we have to move, hurry! There is no time to waste. Come everybody!
- Thank you, Moominpappa, thank you!
Now!
Snork! My only brother!
Stop Snork! Don't jump!
Why have you dragged everybody here?
You are way too young to end your days this tragically. Luckily we got here in time to save you!
Well no you didn't.
- Snork!
It looks like a dangerous experiment.
Nonsense, I have built these wings by myself!
Good argument but anyway...
I've made exact blueprints of them, and these wings are safe.
Why did you stop so suddenly when you were first running down the hill?
I was calculating how much speed I need.
Don't jump, Snork. I don't want to lose you!
Stop nagging Snorkmaiden.
Can you really trust in those wings?
Of course, birds don't fall from the sky either.
Why you don't try wings closer to the ground? So you won't hurt yourself if you fall.
I tried already. I jumped successfully from the roof.
Did you happened to see?
- Well no I didn't.
I wouldn't jump in front of a sissy.
- What was that supposed to mean?
It means that I don't want you to stick your big nose up in my business all the time!
Yours is as big as mine! I just don't want to lose you.
Then don't continue.
- Yes I will!
Come on, behave.
- Look out!
I think that we can't stop your brothers intentions.
Snork, I think you're brave.
Now let's do this! This time I'll take a better start!
Is that Snufkin?
- Where is Snufkin?
You won't see him there, get up here!
- Where is he?
Down there. Snufkin!
Hey!
Did he hear you?
- I don't think so.
Here we go!
- Good luck!
It's going well!
That's Snork.
Oh, Awesome!
- Do you see Snorkmaiden? Your brother is flying headlong!
Oh he made it!
I was sure he was going to make it.
- To be honest, so did I.
Good, good!
Fantastic! The test flight is going to be a success!
Exactly what I thought! He can't wave and fly at the same time!
- You are lowly.
He will fall if he waves with two hands!
Stinky, you are not needed here. Go away immediately!
That thing could be useful...
I will go if you stay.
It would be good for robberies. With that it would be easy to get over high fences!
The wind is taking Snork to the sea.
Why he doesn't turn around and come back?
It could be difficult to change direction.
- He can't turn around?
Of course he can...
Hey, what is this? I can't turn this!
He crashed into a tree!
- Quickly, help him!
Is he dead?
- No it's just bump.
Oh? Looks dead. Where are the wings?
- Still up there.
Snork has probably gotten tired of those wings already. I will take them!
Well? The test flight went well or...?
Yeah, I guess. Except the end.
I'm sure that all you need is just more practice!
Well yeah, if you have enough iodine and bandages.
Hey Snork.
- Yeah?
Are you gonna use those wings anymore?
- What if I don't?
I want them! I want to fly through the sky too! It looks the funnest thing I've ever seen!
The flying features of the wings must be tested more.
Well yeah, that is clear and I could test those for you!
I guess you could help in some way, Moomintroll.
You didn't answer yet. Will I have the wings?
- Yes. Under one condition.
I will do anything!
Now I have blueprints already and the wings are mostly okay to fly. I will need a place to build my gadget.
Yes, you definitely need to.
It doesn't need to be fancy. Just a roof over my head so no one could spy or steal my brilliant invention.
You'll have those wings if you help me.
- It's a deal.
I would have helped anyway, but now that I get those wings I will work double effort!
Excellent, it's settled then.
Maybe you will have other avid helpers as well. Snufkin?
Of course.
Sniff, will you help?
- Yeah but I want something too.
You can borrow those wings!
I don't want to break them. I'm too heavy...
Don't worry about it. I will try to figure out something.
Something nice! I will gladly help!
Sniff, you are so full of goodness.
I'm sure you are going to need an expert's help to build that forge.
Is this hole deep enough already?
No, we Moomins build things thoroughly and I like to mold cement.
- Okay.
I have thought my head through. You can have my worthless machine building book.
...Book?
- You don't want it?
Do you happen to have anything else?
Would you like to have my worthless fountain pen?
I don't write much.
How about my worthless...
- Do you have something that isn't worthless?
A gold coin!
-Yea, that sounds something! Oh boy, a real gold coin!
You are digging a really deep hole there. Stop for a moment and come to eat sandwiches.
In the middle of all this?
- Maybe that hole is deep enough already.
Your brother and Sniff are in the forest.
I know.
Hey Snorkmaiden!
Hey, I'd like to ask something!
- Ask then.
Is true that your brother gave those wings to Moomintroll?
Yes. Moomintroll is helping to build a forge in return.
The wings didn't break during that crash?
My brother is fixing them at the moment and I'm bringing lunch to him so move out of my way.
Can your brother really fix those wings?
- He can fix anything!
You need so much lumber.
The forge needs to be bigger than my flight gadget.
Moominpappa and Moomintroll are digging a deep hole.
Everyone is so nice and helpful.
Snufkin is going to go to get nails.
- Excellent. Write him a note for all the other things as well.
Yes dear brother. You are so methodical.
- Famous inventors need to be.
The airplane forge was ready in record time. It could be Snork's planning skills or that almost everyone in Moominvalley came to help.
Come in!
- Moomintroll is here!
Come in, Moomintroll.
Thank you for everything. You have helped so much that the wings probably won't make up for it.
Building that forge was fun.
I changed the shape of the wings. Now it's easier to rise and land. Also it's easier to turn.
Thank you. I'm so excited that I probably won't sleep much tonight.
When are you going to try wings?
- Tomorrow.
Be careful!
Start practicing close to the ground before getting higher. I would feel terrible if something happened.
Alright!
Where are you going to practice?
- I don't know yet.
Maybe that little hill close to the cliff.
- Good, that is not dangerous. See you there!
Hey, I don't see the wings!
If you came through the patio door you should have seen them. They are on the table.
On the table? There was nothing there.
You were right! My wings have disappeared!
- Of course I'm right.
What has happened to them?
- Someone has stolen them!
What is the matter with you two?
Someone has stolen Moomintroll's wings!
Maybe they're not really stolen.
- Yes they are! And I know who took them!
Where should we start looking for the wings?
Stinky!
- You again. That didn't take long.
Stinky, wait! Those wings are mine!
- I knew that you stole them!
Stop you slimebag!
- Don't even think about it!
Wait, I will let you borrow wings later!
- No no, I need these wings to speed up my career!
Look out Moomintroll!
You bugs! With these wings I'm going to be a master criminal!
Stinky is a disgusting bandit.
- You shouldn't have left those wings outside.
Who would have guessed that Stinky was going to steal from us. We are his friends. Almost.
But my coin is safe.
Don't be sad Moomintroll. We will get the wings back.
I'll punch his nose!
Stinky is drifting to the sea!
Hey, what is this? Turn around you damned apparatus!
Stinky didn't know how to handle the wings and was drifting further and further.
He got a bath! The wings are probably trashed.
Snork will build new wings for you.
- Damn Stinky.